today we're going to take a look at some
of the coolest and most useful CSS
Frameworks that you need to know about
we will take a look at Frameworks on
different categories like general
purpose Frameworks utility based
Frameworks classless Frameworks
specialized framework super lightweight
Frameworks and finally react UI
Frameworks if you don't know what they
are or why you need them a CSS framework
is just a collection of pre-made
components or utilities like buttons
navigation bars drop downs forms Etc
that you can use to move quicker and
finish your projects faster a general
purpose Frameworks are all in one
toolkit for building websites they are
big bulky and they've got everything you
need grids typography buttons forms
models alerts accordions Etc bootstrap
is a super popular
well-established CSS framework that is
great for beginners and experts it
offers a very wide range of pre-designed
components which makes it a go-to choice
for quick prototyping however its
popularity can be a double-edged sword
as many websites using bootstrap can end
up looking similar unless you put effort
on applying a custom styling Foundation
is another very robust flexible
framework that is excellent for creating
responsive designs it is highly
customizable allowing you to build
complex layouts with ease but it might
have a steeper learning curve compared
to other Frameworks websites built with
Foundation include Mini Cooper Pixar Dr
Martens Ford Outback Steakhouse and many
more Bulma is one of my favorite ones
it's a lightweight CSS framework based
on flexbox that is easy to learn and use
with a clean syntax and good
documentation it does not have as many
pre-designed components as a bootstrap
or Foundation which makes it more
lightweight and easier to learn also
because it is really easy to customize
no Bulma website looks the same
utility-based Frameworks are like Lego
blocks of CSS they give you a bunch of
small single purpose classes that you
can mix and match to build your website
they don't have pre-made components such
as form or a gallery like the ones in
the previous category instead they have
a bunch of classes like padding top 20
or font size large they might take a bit
of getting used to but once you get the
hang of it you can create some really
Unique Designs Tailwind CSS is by far
the most popular framework on this
category it has got utility classes for
almost everything you will need flexbox
and grid facing sizing typography
backgrounds Transformations
interactivity Etc it even has a just in
time compiler that creates classes on
demand when you need to use arbitrary
values because all it does is give you
some CSS classes and no Tailwind website
looks the same open props is another
utility based framework that just like
Tailwind comes with a lot of building
blocks but unlike Tailwind those
building blocks don't come on the shape
of class names on open props they come
on the shape of CSS variables open props
comes with a bunch of pre-made CSS
variables that you call from your CSS
code this way you keep your HTML clean
of class names which is something that
people that don't like Tailwind CSS
complain about open props has CSS
variables for colors gradients Shadows
aspect ratios typography animations
sizes media queries and more base CSS is
another utility based framework and just
like Tailwind it uses class names but
unlike Tailwind base CSS is pretty small
it only weighs 2.13 kilobytes it comes
with just enough utilities to help you
get the foundation of your design before
adding extra custom code going from one
extreme to the next classless Frameworks
are CSS Frameworks that don't require
you to predefined class names instead
they apply Styles directly to the HTML
elements making them ideal for simple
projects and quick prototypes all you
have to do is import the CSS file of
these Frameworks and your page will
automatically look great the water CSS
is super minimalistic but it does the
job well it comes with dark and light
theme it is responsive and it makes
forms and buttons look really nice
mvp.css comes with a layout system as
well it has cards with shadows
accordions Stables headers and Heroes
all you have to do is use the correct
HTML tag and MVP CSS will make it look
good specialized Frameworks are designed
to do one thing and do it well
materialize is a specialized framework
that implements Google's material design
system CSS is a framework for building
retro Apple inspired interfaces it comes
with buttons menus text boxes titles
dialogues and more components that will
make your website look like Apple
Computers did back in 1984. Nest CSS is
a framework with buttons inputs forms
containers tables and even icons with
the style of the Nintendo Entertainment
System PS1 CSS inspired by Nest CSS is
the same but on the styles of the
PlayStation 1. and in the case that you
like Windows you can use 98 CSS a CSS
library for building interfaces that
look like Windows 98 it comes with all
the forms sliders title bars tabs tables
and more if you prefer a more modern
flavor of Windows you can use XP CSS
which has got the same components but in
the Windows XP style or you can use 7
CSS if you like the Windows 7 style more
Bosch there is another specialized
framework for developing a responsive
email templates if you have experience
with email template development you know
that it sucks there are so many email
clients so many devices and not all
modern CSS works on email templates
Butler comes with a bunch of components
for your email templates that have been
tested on email clients like Apple Mail
Outlook Gmail Yahoo iPhones and Androids
super lightweight Frameworks are the
featherweights of CSS Frameworks they
are all about being as light and fast as
possible providing just the essentials
they are great for small projects or
when you need your website to be super
quick Joda is a necro framework that
comes with grids CSS variables buttons
navigations and More in only 3 KB of CSS
Pico CSS is also super small it has a
couple of classes for grids tables and
containers but apart from that it is
almost classless and very easy to use
all the Frameworks on this video can in
theory be used with react but there are
some Frameworks that are react specific
Frameworks and com with many pre-built
react components and very nice things my
favorite react specific framework is
chakra UI chakra UI not only comes with
the beautiful components but it also
helps you write less JavaScript code as
well it comes with models notifications
alerts menus loaders switches and many
more components that need some kind of
JavaScript logic and it abstracts it all
for you Mantine is a library of a lot
ready to use react component just like
with chakra it not only looks nice but
it also abstracts a lot of logic for you
and design developed by Alibaba has got
a ton of components and is designed for
Enterprise level applications it's got a
unique design language that's clean and
professional but that some people find
hard to customize material UI is a
library of react UI components that
implements Google's material design it
has a ton of components that follow the
material design guidelines it's super
customizable if you're a fan of material
design you're going to love material UI
and next UI is a fairly new framework
that was inspired by the design system
of versaille it's got a clean modern
design and it's got dark mode support it
is on beta which means that it has some
ready to use components but not all the
ones that you may need for a real life
project just yet that's it for this
video I hope that you liked it and I
hope that you discovered Frameworks that
you did not know about that can save you
time in the future let me know in the
comments what your favorite framework is
my favorite ones are Bulma telwyn and
chakra UI and the Retro apple one as
well if there is a framework that you
like that I forgot to mention leave it
in the comments so we can all check it
out and don't forget that if you want to
learn things like JavaScript python
react react native gold Dart flutter
among many others for absolutely free
all you have to do is click the link
below if you join any of our many free
core that you can take right now for
absolutely free with me click the link
below and I will see you there
see you on the next one bye
[Music]
foreign